Guide to the Dorothy Norman Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Dorothy Norman Papers,
1923-1978
Norman, Dorothy, 1905-1997.
60 linear ft. (ca. 25,000 items in 145 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079170
Biographical Note
Journalist. Dorothy Stecher Norman was active for many years in a wide range of social and political movements.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, reports, pamphlets, and clippings of Norman. Among the subjects represented are health, population control, civil liberties, refugees, exiled governments and peoples of World War II, United Nations, education, delinquency, race relations, emerging nationalities, censorship, and foreign aid. Much of the correspondence in the collection centers around Mrs. Norman's column in THE NEW YORK POST in the 1940s. Organizations in the collection include Civil Liberties Union, Americans for Democratic Action, American Citizens Committee for Economic Aid Abroad, Women's City Club, American Emergency Food Committee for India, Urban League, Liberal Party, Citizens Union, Free Germany Movement, Free China Movement, and United World Federation. Also included are correspondence, manuscripts, research materials, and printed materials dealing with Norman's research and writing on India. There are two working manuscripts, one on India, the other on Nehru. Also, a fragmentary manuscript of her memoirs and the beginnings of a study of Alfred Stieglitz.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 12 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Topical Files
Seties IV: Clippings by Others
Series V: Printed Materials
Series VI: Manuscripts
Series VII: Subject Files
Series VIII: Correspondence
Series IX: Indian
Series X: 1982 Gift
Series XI: 1991 Gift
Series XII: Printed Materials
Subjects
United World Federation.; United Nations.; American Civil Liberties Union.; Americans for Democratic Action.; Women's City Club of New York.; Urban League of Greater New York.; Liberal Party of New York State.; Citizens Union of the City of New York.; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971.; Bohlen, Charles E. (Charles Eustis), 1904-1974.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Mountbatten of Burma, Louis Mountbatten, Earl, 1900-1979.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946.; Nehru, Jawaharlal, 1889-1964.; India--Social conditions.; India--Politics and government.; United States--Social conditions.; United States--Politics and government.; China--Social conditions.; Germany--Social conditions.; Newspapers--Sections, columns, etc.; Health.; African Americans--History.; Birth control.; Civil rights.; Refugees.; Governments in exile.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Photographers.; Juvenile delinquency.; Education.; Race relations.; Censorship.; Economic assistance.; Social problems.; World politics.; Statesmen.; American Citizens Committee for Economic Aid Abroad.; Free Germany Movement.; Free China Movement.; American Emergency Food Committee for India.; Women in politics.; Women journalists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1966 M-66 Norman, Dorothy S. Gift
Alternate Formats
Pearl S. Buck letters are on microfilm.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Acheson, Dean To Dorothy Norman, [Washington], 8 March 1961, (1 page t.l.s. (with related material))
  - Bohlen, Charles E. To Dorothy Norman, Washington, 19 September 1962, (1 page t.l.s.)
  - Dulles, Allen W. To Dorothy Norman, Washington, 14 Feb. 1953 - 1 June 1959, (5 t.l.s.)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H. To Dorothy Norman, Washington, 25 May 1962, (1 page t.l.s.)
  - Mountbatten, Lord Louis To Dorothy Norman, London, 21 September 1962, (1 page t.l.s. (with carbon replies))
  - Stevenson, Adlai To Dorothy Norman, [n.p.], 1956-1962, (5 t.l.s.)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
- Series III: Topical Files
  - ADA (Box 3)
  - Africa; Algeria (Box 4)
  - Art (Box 5)
  - Art (Box 6)
  - Art (Box 7)
  - Asia (Box 8)
  - Asia; Atomic Energy; Austria (Box 9)
  - Birth Control (Box 10)
  - Birth Control (Box 11)
  - Books (Box 12)
  - Britain; Burma (Box 13)
  - Carnegie Endowment; Children; China; Citizens Budget Committee (Box 14)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 15)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 16)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 17)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 18)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 19)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 20)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 21)
  - Congressional Record; Co-operatives; Courth; Cuba; Cultural Freedom; Democrats Convention 1948; Disarmament; Doorway for 20th Century (Box 22)
  - Education (Box 23)
  - Education (Box 24)
  - Foreign Aid, 1952 (Box 25)
  - Foreign Aid, 1953-54 (Box 26)
  - Foreign Aid, 1955-56 (Box 27)
  - Foreign Aid, 1956-57 (Box 28)
  - Foreign Aid, 1957-58 (Box 29)
  - Foreign Aid, 1957-58 (& others) (Box 30)
  - Foreign Aid (Box 31)
  - Foreign Aid (Box 32)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 33)
  - Foreign Policy, 1947-48 (Box 34)
  - Foreign Policy (Box 35)
  - Food; Foundations; France; Fund for the Republic; Gardens; Germany; Guild Hall (Box 36)
  - Health (Box 37)
  - Health (Box 38)
  - Health (Box 39)
  - Health (Box 40)
  - Housing; Human Rights; Immigration (Box 41)
  - India, 1940-1950 (Box 42)
  - India, 1951-1960 (Box 43)
  - India Clippings (Box 44)
  - Institute for Pacific Relations; International (Box 45)
  - International (Box 46)
  - International (Box 47)
  - International relations; Israel (Jews) (Box 48)
  - Israel (Jews) (Box 49)
  - Israel (Jews); Japan (Box 50)
  - Labor (Box 51)
  - Latin America; League for International Democracy; Mexico; Miscellaneous (Box 52)
  - Mutual Security, 1951; 52 & general (Box 53)
  - Mutual Security, 1952 (Box 54)
  - Mutual Security, 1953-55 (Box 55)
  - "The Nation"; National affairs; National Committee for Effective Congress; New York City; New York State (Box 56)
  - New York (City & State) (Box 57)
  - New York (City & State) (Box 58)
  - Norman, Dorothy: Mss. (Box 59)
  - Norman, Dorothy: Mss. (Box 60)
  - Norman, Dorothy: Miscellaneous columns (Box 61)
  - Norman, Dorothy: Miscellaneous columns (Box 62)
  - Norman, Dorothy: Miscellaneous (Box 63)
  - Ottley: "New World A-Coming" (Box 64)
  - Politics (national) (Box 65)
  - Politics (national) (Box 66)
  - Postwar (Box 67)
  - Postwar (Box 68)
  - Printing & Type; Puerto Rico (Box 69)
  - Race Relations (discrimination) (Box 70)
  - Race Relations (discrimination) (Box 71)
  - Race Relations (discrimination) (Box 72)
  - Race Relations (discrimination) (Box 73)
  - Race Relations (discrimination) (Box 74)
  - Race Relations (discrimination) (Box 75)
  - Race Relations (Box 76)
  - Race Relations (Box 77)
  - Refugees (Box 78)
  - Religion; Roosevelt, Eleanor; Roosevelt, F.D.R.; Russia; Save Our Schools Committee (Box 79)
  - Science; Society for the Prevention of World War III; South America; State Department (Box 80)
  - Theater; "Tomorrow" magazine; Travel (Box 81)
  - United Nations (Box 82)
  - United Nations (Box 83)
  - United Nations (Box 84)
  - United Nations, 1951-1958 (Box 85)
  - U.S. government; United World Federation; Wallace, H.A. (Box 86)
  - Welfare; Women (Box 87)
  - World government; World Rehabilitation Fund; Yalta Record (Box 88)
  - Youth (Box 89)
  - Youth (Box 90)
- Seties IV: Clippings by Others
  - Clippings by others: A-Ki (Box 91)
  - Clippings by others: Kn-W (Box 92)
- Series V: Printed Materials
  - Printed materials; "Twice A Year" (Box 93)
  - Books (Box 94)
  - Books (Box 95)
  - Pamphlets (Box 96)
  - Reports, etc. (Box 97)
  - Printed materials by and about Dorothy Norman (Box 98)
- Series VI: Manuscripts
  - Manuscripts and Typescripts (Box 99)
- Series VII: Subject Files
  - Subject folders (Box 100)
- Series VIII: Correspondence
  - Correspondence (names) A-Z (Box 101)
  - Correspondence (general) (Box 102)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1943 (1); Albert and Maty Lasker correspondence; Edward Bernays correspondence (Box 103)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1944 (Box 104)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 105)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1971 (Box 106)
- Series IX: Indian
  1975 Gift
  - India (printed, also carbon copies of mansucripts) (Box 107)
  - India (printed material) (Box 108-122)
- Series X: 1982 Gift
  - Bangladesh to India - Art, Culture, etc. (Box 127)
  - India - Correspondence to India - Manuscript (Box 128)
  - India - Manuscript (con't.) (Box 129)
  - India - Misc. Notes to India - Research Material (Box 130)
  - Memoirs to Mythology, Astrology, Religion, etc. (Box 131)
  - Nehru - Correspondence to Nehru - Notes on first visit to U.S. (Box 132)
  - Nehru - Primary source material - Chapters VIII-X (Box 133)
  - Nehru - Primary source material - Chapters XI-XIII (Box 134)
  - Nehru - Primary source material - Chapters XIV-XVI (Box 135)
  - New York Foundation to Stieglitz (Box 136)
- Series XI: 1991 Gift
  - Asia Society (Box 137)
  - Gandhi, Indira (Box 137)
  - India - Arts (Box 137)
  - India - Correspondence - Syracuse A-Z (Box 138)
  - India - Correspondence - With Various Governments (Box 138)
  - India - Correspondence - Individual Folders A-M (Box 139)
  - India - Correspondence - Individual Folders M-Z (Box 140)
  - India - History (Box 141)
  - India - Manuscripts (incomplete) (Box 141)
  - India - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 141)
  - India - U.S. Relations (Box 141)
  - India League (Box 141)
  - Memoir - Manuscript (incomplete) (Box 141)
  - Memoir - Notes (Box 141)
  - Mythology, Astrology and Religion (Box 142)
  - McCarthy, Senator Joseph (Box 143)
  - Nehru, Jawaharlal - Research materials & notes (Box 143)
- Series XII: Printed Materials
  - Oficial publications of the Government of India (Box 144)
  - Oficial publications of the Government of the United States (Box 144)